Guide to the Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine Records, 1878-1972 AIS.2017.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine Records
1878-1972
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine (Pa.)
AIS.2017.01
11 Linear Feet (16 boxes)
This collection contains material related to the founding of the Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine in the late 1800s, its membership and ongoing business and presentations, and its decline in the 1970s.
History
The Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine was founded in 1889 for "the promotion of the science and art of medicine," according to its charter. It continued to function for a century as a social club for physicians, a forum for presentation of medical research and discussion of medical cases, and, through its library, a source of medical reference information to Pittsburgh and the surrounding areas.
According to Theodore Diller, an early member, the Academy was founded by a group of doctors unhappy with the atmosphere and depth of scientific inquiry offered by the Allegheny County Medical Society. Early meetings were held in a room near the Coroner's Office, though the Academy would purchase a building at 322 N. Craig Street in Pittsburgh in 1916 where they held regular business meetings, banquets, and, most notably, presentations of scientific papers and research. Applications for admission into the Academy were reviewed by a committee and members were expected to attend meetings regularly and pay annual dues.
The Academy leased a medical library from the Pittsburgh Medical Library Association in 1896; the Academy purchased the library soon thereafter. Access to the library was free to Academy members as well as to university and college students and saw regular use by both groups for many years. By the 1930s, the library totaled over 15,000 volumes, but by the 1950s other medical libraries, including the library of the University of Pittsburgh Medical School, gained prominence and led to decreased use of the Academy's collection. The library was sold to the University of Massachusetts Medical School in 1967.
In 1968 the Academy sold its building on Craig Street and moved to the offices of the Allegheny County Medical Society. Regular Academy meetings and scientific programs continued until at least the early 1970s, though the date that the Academy was dissolved remains unclear.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
The records consist of legal and administrative files, corresponence, membership records, publications, and meeting minutes and programs documenting the activity of the Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine. Of particular note are the documents relating to the medical library, which was heavily used by area physicians and medical students from its initial lease by the Academy in 1896 through the 1940s. Additionally, there are substantial legal and administrative records detailing the work of Academy committees and individual members in Western Pennsylvania and, in some cases, regionally and nationally. There is also some documentation of the leisure and social activity of the Academy, through meeting minutes, the group's non-scientific publications and plays, and photographs of banquets. Finally, the scientific presentations at meetings of the Academy are well-documented, including programs and notices from meetings, brief minutes for meetings, and the full text of many of the scientific papers presented between 1914 and 1935. Some papers are presentations of original research or informative presentations on disease strains and new treatments, while others are analyses of individual medical case studies.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into the following series:
Series I. Legal Documents, 1890-1968
Series II. Academy Minutes, 1889-1967
Series III. Council, Board of Trustees, and Board of Directors, 1894-1972
Series IV. Annual Reports, 1895-1962
Series V. Treasurer, 1927-1969
Series VI. Library, 1891-1968
Series VII. Meeting Programs and Notices, 1905-1972
Series VIII. Membership, 1891-1967
Series IX. Correspondence, 1916-1968
Series X. Profiles of Members and Associates, 1898-1966
Series XI. Committees, 1895-1972
Series XII. Lists of Officers and Awards, 1890-1972
Series XIII. Publications and Plays, 1905-1972
Series XIV. Scientific Papers, 1917-1935
Series XV. Photographs, 1905
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the University of Pittsburgh's Falk Medical Library on July 30, 2012. This collection was separated from the Falk Library Medical School History Collection (UA.2012.28) in December 2016.
Related Material
Falk Library Medical School History collection (1892-1993). UA.90.36.7, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Cortland W.W. Elkin Papers (1943-1963). MFF 2221. Heinz History Center.
Diller, Theodore W. [1908]. "Montaigne's estimate of medicine and the medical profession..." Paper read before the Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine. Princeton University Library Rare Books and Special Collections, 3273.646.
Previous Citation
Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine Records, 1889-1972, AIS.2017.01, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Health and medicine; Associations; Medicine -- Societies, etc.; Medical libraries; Jackson, Chevalier; Diller, Theodore; Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine (Pa.)
- Legal Documents, 1890-1968; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Documents relating to the founding, operation, and decline of the Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine, including the constitution, bylaws, and charter, as well as library and real estate documents. Of particular note are the documents relating to the lease and sale of the library to the Academy, as well as documents related to the purchase and subsequent sale of the Academy's building on Craig Street in Pittsburgh.
  - Constitution and by-laws, June 18, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution and by-laws revision, June 10, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Constitution and by-laws, with officer lists and lists of members, 1889-1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Application for amendment of charter, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Charter, constitution, and by-laws, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Charter and by-laws, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Charter and by-laws, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Changes to by-laws, 1920-1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Member subscription agreement, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Real estate lease, purchase, and insurance, 1903-1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Library lease and agreement, 1896-1904 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Savings bonds and bank records, 1942-1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Statement of account, building committee, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sale of building, 1967-68 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Academy Minutes, 1889-1967; II.
  Minutes from Academy business meetings and scientific meetings. Some bound volumes of minutes contain minutes from both business and scientific meetings.
  - Business Meetings, 1889-1962; 1.
    Minutes from Academy business meetings include reports on committee work, notes on meeting attendance, election of officers, committee members, and new members, and any motions made or discussions by the members attending the meeting.
    - Minutes, November 11, 1889-May 22, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Minutes, September 18, 1890-December 14, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Minutes, January 9, 1893-September 21, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Minutes, May 4, 1896-June 26, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Minutes, September 4, 1899-October 20, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Minutes, November 3, 1902-May 28, 1907 (Box 4, Volume 1)
    - Minutes, September 29, 1925-February 7, 1939 (Box 4, Volume 2)
    - Minutes, February 8, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Minutes, September 23, 1947-April 10, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Scientific Meetings, 1914-1962; 2.
    Scientific meeting minutes include names of speakers, topics of papers or discussions, dates, locations and times of meetings and, in some cases, the numbers of members and guests attending.
    - Minutes, April 28, 1914- January 26, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Minutes, February 23, 1926-March 12, 1940 (Box 6, Volume 1)
    - Minutes, October 14, 1947-March 13, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Combined Business Meetings and Scientific Meetings, 1907-1967; 3.
    The two earliest folders in this subseries are bound volumes. The contents of the two later folders were originally kept in three-ring binders; they have been removed from the binders but their contents have been kept together. These folders contain both business and scientific meeting minutes. Scientific meeting minutes include names of speakers, topics of papers or discussions, dates, locations and times of meetings and, in some cases, the numbers of members and guests attending. Minutes from business meetings include reports on committee work, notes on meeting attendance, election of officers, committee members, and new members, and any motions made or discussions by the members attending the meeting. The later
    - Minutes, business meetings (1914-1925) and scientific meetings (1907-1914), October 1, 1907--May 12, 1925 (Box 5, Volume 1)
    - Minutes, busniess meetings (1939-1947) and scientific meetings (1940-1947)., May 23, 1939--May 27, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Minutes, business and scientific meetings, October 9, 1962-November 9, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Minutes, business and scientific meetings, January 11, 1966-November 17, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Council, Board of Trustees, and Board of Directors, 1894-1972; III.
  Documents created by the governing bodies of the Academy. The Board of Trustees appears to have been a short-term body within the Academy. By the time of the publication of its 1920 charter, the Academy was governed by a Board of Directors and a Council. Members of the Board of Directors were elected for 5-year terms and oversaw the property and financial affairs of the Academy. Councilors were elected for 3-year terms and supervised the scientific meetings, including inviting guest speakers, and was tasked with reprimanding Fellows for conduct or non-payment of dues.
  - Council, correspondence, 1927-1952 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Council, minutes, February 3, 1948-December 8, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Council, report, 1894-1895 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Board of Directors (1920-1947) and Council (1916-1947), minutes, January 4, 1916--May 27, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Board of Directors, correspondence, 1920-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors, minutes, September 23, 1947-October 2, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees, report, January 13, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Annual Reports, 1895-1962; IV.
  Annual reports from Academy officers. Reports of the President and Secretary generally center on attendance at meetings, election and elevation of Fellows, and the death of Fellows or their withdrawl from membership in the Academy. Treasurer reports include lists of income and expenditures. Library reports include statistics on the acquisition of new materials and numbers of reference questions answered. There are also statistics on the circulation of library materials as well as the number of patrons that consult materials in the library itself, in addition to substantial written commentary on the statistics by C.W.W. Elkin, the Academy's medical librarian.
  - President, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Corresponding secretary, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Secretary, 1948-1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Treasurer, 1895-1952 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Librarian, 1935-1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Treasurer, 1927-1969; V.
  Documentation of the Academy's financial transactions, including correspondence with the secretary and members about payment of dues, ledger books of Academy expenditures and receipts, and a declaration of assets and investments just after the sale of the library and Craig St. building.
  - Correspondence, 1927-1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Expenditures, 1937-1950 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Expenditures, 1950-1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Receipts, 1937-1949 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Receipts, 1949-1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Statement of assets and investments, May 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Library, 1891-1968; VI.
  Documentation regarding the Academy's library, including its initial lease, the sale of the library to the Academy, its patterns of use, and the sale of the library to the University of Massachusetts in 1967. Of particular note are the library's original catalogue ledger book and the register of library users that show robust use of the library's assets by members of the Academy and the Allegheny County Medical Society, as well as medical students at the University of Pittsburgh until the late 1940s, when students and local physicians used the medical and dental library at the University of Pittsburgh more regularly than the Academy's. There is considerable documentation of discussions around the sale of the library in the correspondence, including "Suggestions and Recommendations Concerning Space and Facilities for the Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine Library," a report by Daniel Pfoutz, of the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh.
  - Pittsburgh Medical Association Library Catalogue, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Pittsburgh Medical Library Association, Minutes, November 25, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Pittsburgh Academy of Medicine, negotiations on the library, 1895-1904 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bookplates, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Library catalogue (ledger), 1900 (Box 6, Volume 2)
  - Accession book, 1895-1928 (Box 15, Volume 2)
  - Accession book, 1928-38 (Box 16, Volume 1)
  - Register of library users, 1907-30 (Box 15, Volume 1)
  - Register of library users, 1930-37 (Box 13, Volume 2)
  - Register of library users, 1938-41 (Box 14, Volume 1)
  - Register of library users, 1941-47 (Box 14, Volume 2)
  - Register of library users, 1947-53 (Box 14, Volume 3)
  - Register of library users, 1953-57 (Box 10, Volume 2)
  - Register of library users, 1958-62 (Box 6, Volume 3)
  - Newsclippings, 1958-1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, general, 1916-1954 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence with Allegheny County Medical Society, 1935-1946 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, evaluation and sale of library, 1961-1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Meeting Programs and Notices, 1905-1972; VII.
  Public announcements and programs for Academy meetings, including agendas, names of speakers, dates and times.
  - Meeting programs (loose), 1910-11 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Meeting programs and notices, 1905-09 (Box 7, Volume 1)
  - Meeting programs and notices, 1909-15 (Box 7, Volume 2)
  - Meeting programs and notices, 1915-23 (Box 8, Volume 1)
  - Meeting programs and notices, 1924-30 (Box 9, Volume 1)
  - Meeting programs and notices, 1931-38 (Box 9, Volume 2)
  - Meeting programs and notices, 1938-47 (Box 10, Volume 1)
  - Meeting programs and notices, 1948-57 (Box 11, Volume 1)
  - Meeting programs and notices, 1957-66 (Box 11, Volume 2)
  - Meeting programs and notices, 1969-72 (Box 13, Volume 1)
- Membership, 1891-1967; VIII.
  Lists of and correspondence with Academy fellows and applicants, including membershp lists and logs, recognition of members, and rejection of applications. Candidates elected to membership were known as fellows, and could be elevated to Associate Fellows, Resident Fellows, Honorary Fellows and Benefactors, depending upon the quality of their meidcal research and/or practice, the length of time they had been Academy Fellows, and their record of distinguished service, either to scientific inquiry generally or to the Academy in particular.
  - Attendance log, 1928-1949 (Box 8, Volume 2)
  - Candidates elected to associate fellowship, 1919-1935 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Candidates elected to associate fellowship, 1936-1941 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Candidates elected to associate fellowship, 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Candidates elected to associate fellowship, 1947-1966 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Candidates proposed for associate fellowship, 1891-1952 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Candidates rejected by Fellowship Committee, 1931-40 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Candidates rejected by vote, 1929-1945 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence regarding attendance, 1921-1953 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence regarding deinquent dues, 1932-1967 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence to fellows not signing constitution, 1940-63 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Fellows attaining the age of 65, 1920-1967 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Fellows dropped from the Academy, 1921-1953 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Fellows in active military service, 1918-1954 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Letters of resignation, 1920-1967 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Members elevated to Resident Fellowship, 1932-47 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Non-resident fellows, 1918-47 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Roll books and membership lists, 1891-1904 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Roll books and membership lists, 1905-1920 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Roll books and membership lists, 1921-27 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Roll books and membership lists, 1927-1939 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Roll books and membership lists, 1939-1948 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1916-1968; IX.
  Contains correspondence to and from the Academy about Academy business and medical topics, including correspondence documenting the Academy's building purchase and upkeep, its involvement in political and scientific endeavors, and the Academy's lecture series. Also included is a folder of correspondence with Mary W. Lynch, the Academy's medical librarian and secretary, largely about general Academy business. Of particular note is the 1878 postcard invitation from Daniel March to Frank LeMoyne that documents an early meeting for the purposese of establishing a medical society in Pittsburgh's East End.
  - Establishing a medical society, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1927-1947 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Property fund, 1920-1922 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Facilities, 1920-1961 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Students' medical society, 1925-1935 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Cyrus Henry Neff murder trial, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Pittsburgh Medical Bulletin, 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Lye legistation bill, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Index Medicus, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Annual lectures, 1940-1968 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Thomas Grier Simonton Memorial Lectures, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Social Security and Department of Treasury, 1939-1954 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - General correspondence with the Academy's library assistant/secretary, 1916-1967 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Profiles of Members and Associates, 1898-1966; X.
  Correspondence and newspaper clippings regarding Academy members and associates. Folders generally contain newsclippings, correspondence, and/or copies of papers presented or published by Academy members. Of particular note are B.A. Cohoe's notebooks from his medical school classes in the 1890s, which contain hand-drawn representations of plant structure, human and animal anatomy, and cell structure.
  - Dr. W.E. Carson, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Dr. B.A. Cohoe, correspondence and scholarly work, 1932-1944 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Dr. B.A. Cohoe, student notebooks, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Dr. B.A. Cohoe, student notebooks, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Dr. Theodore Diller, 1931-1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Dr. Henry C. Flood, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Dr. William R. Hunt, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Dr. Chevalier Jackson, 1924-1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dr. Francis W. Joyce, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dr. James P. Kerr, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sen. Robert A. Taft, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Dr. J. Huber Wagner, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Committees, 1895-1972; XI.
  Reports of and correspondence about the work of Academy committees. Folders generally contain correspondence between committee members, as well as correspondence to and from the committee chair. Some folders also contain intermittent committee reports to the Academy Board. The scientific program committee folder also contains some schedules of lectures and presentations, and the annual dinner committee folder contains programs and menus from the Academy's 50th Anniversary Dinner in 1939. The necrology committee folder contains correspondence, including sympathy cards, with the families of deceased Academy members.
  - Admissions committee, 1895-1920 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Annual dinner committee, 1921-1960 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Auditing committee, 1921-1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Biographic Quesionnaire Committee, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Editorial and Publicity Committee, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Fellowship committee, 1927-1967 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Future Planning Committee, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Health Insurance Committee, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Laboratory committee, 1896 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Necrology committee, 1919-1962 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Nominations committee, 1924-1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Nurses' directory committee, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Scientific program committee, 1927-1947 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Officers and Awards, 1890-1972; XII.
  Lists of officers, including past presidents and committee members, as well as awardees of the Academy.
  - Past presidents, 1890-1967 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Officers and committees, 1925-1971 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Man of the Year awardees, 1966-1972 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Scholarship members, 1967-1972 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Academy members who are officers of the Pennsylvania Medical Society, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Publications and Plays, 1905-1972; XIII.
  This series contains non-scientific publications documenting the Academy's function as a social club for physicians. Included are a copy of Academy Warwhoop, a comedic newspaper that includes short satirical articles, poems, and cartoons about Academy members as well as scripts and programs from Academy plays. Additionally, there is a bound volume of caricatures of Academy members.
  - Academy Warwhoop (comedy newspaper), December 13, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - As We See Each Other (book of caricatures of Academy fellows), 1910 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Annual Play, Programs, 1966-1977 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Script, "Dinner Reservations Will Include the Privilege of Inspection 'A Model Child Welfare Clinic' Under the Personal Direction of Doctor Half Price", undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Scientific papers, 1917-1935; XIV.
  Typewritten and handwritten copies of research papers and discussions of cases presented at the Academy's scientific meetings. The 1914-1915 folder contains a record of the discussion that followed a presentation exclusively and no texts of the presentation.
  - Discussion following scientific paper, 1914-1915 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Scientific papers, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Dr. Moses Have Baker, "Report of 30 Cases of Lobar Pneumonia Caused by Type I Pneumococcus, Treated with Type I Antipneumococcus Serum", April 30, 1918; 1.
    - Dr. Moses Have Baker, "Some Observations on the Wassermann Test", undated; 2.
    - Dr. Everhardt, "Pyloric Stenosis", undated; 3.
    - Dr. Ellis M. Frost, "Case Report", March 26, 1918; 4.
    - Dr. Clarence H. Ingram, "Melaena Neoatorum", March, 1917; 5.
    - Dr. C. B. Maits, "Egg Poisoning: With History of a Case", undated; 6.
    - Dr. F. W. Mathewson, "Acute Suppurative Cholecystitis Complication Typhoid Fever", February 6, 1917; 7.
    - Dr. Maxwell, "Ether Anaesthesia", undated; 8.
    - Dr. Edward E. Mayer, "The Sciaticas", undated; 9.
    - Dr. Charles A. Stillwagen, Pelvic Inflammatory Disease, undated; 10.
    - Dr. Frank L. Todd, Cancer, undated; 11.
    - Dr. Frank L. Todd, Surgical Conditions found in the Abdomen, undated; 12.
    - Dr. Frederich B. Utley, "An Analysis of 998 Consecutive Complete Blood Counts", undated; 13.
    - "Acute Intestinal Obstruction", undated; 14.
    - "Conservative Surgery of the Seminal Vesicles", undated; 15.
    - "Curettage--its Use and Abuse", February 13, 1918; 16.